A Guide to the Beverly Willis Architectural Papers, 1954-1998
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Beverly Willis Architectural Papers 1954-1998
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Ms92-019
100 linear feet; includes 45 linear feet of architecture drawings, maps, plans, and other oversize materials and 51 linear feet of additional records, including photographs, slides, computer tapes, and videotapes.
Beverly Willis
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Beverly Willis donated samples of her designs to Virginia Tech in 1992. This gift was followed, in 2000, with a donation of the bulk of the records and designs from her architectural career.
Alternative Form
The Imagebase at Virginia Tech's Special Collections contains nearly 500 digital images of Willis' work, arranged by project, and a folio of Willis family photographs.
Biographical/Historical Information
Beverly Willis, FAIA Architect, artist, and writer, was one of perhaps three women architects in the United States to own her own sizeable architecture firm between 1958 and 1990 and the only woman in San Francisco, California, to have her own practice there for 17 years. Her book, Invisible Images: The Silent Language of Architecture, published by the National Building Museum, describes her design philosophy.
She was the first woman appointed to the Building Research Advisory Board of the National Academy of Science, the first appointed to the Federal Construction Council, and its first woman chair. She was the first woman elected president of the American Institute of Architects, California Council; and the Golden Gate Chapter of Lambda Alpha Society.
Willis played a major role in the revitalization of San Francisco neighborhoods after World War II. She renovated commercial spaces in the Jackson Square area and Union Street, redesigned Glide Church, designed the San Francisco Ballet Building, and won an international competition to design the Yerba Buena Gardens development downtown.
Beverly Willis was born February 17, 1928, in Tulsa, Oklahoma, to Ralph William Willis, founder of the National Tool Company, and Margaret Elizabeth Porter, a nurse. She had one sibling, Ralph Gerald Willis. Both Willis and her brother were placed in an orphanage when their parents divorced in 1934.
Taking advantage of the increased opportunities available to women with the advent of World War II, Willis learned welding, riveting, electrical wiring, carpentry, and how to fly an airplane--skills that reflected the fiercely independent qualities that emerged in her personality when she was in the institutional environment of the orphanage. After the war, she enrolled in an aeronautical engineering program at Oregon State University, but withdrew after two years to work at a lithographer's studio. She then studied at the San Francisco Art Institute until relocating to Hawaii. In 1954 she received a B.A. in Fine Art from the University of Hawaii.
After graduation, Willis received a series of design commissions that led to her interest in architecture. Fueled by the friendship and ideas of entrepreneur Henry Kaiser, Willis returned to San Francisco in 1960 to open a firm that designed furniture and interiors for offices, created mixed-media art for clients that included United Airlines, and re-worked supermarket displays. Despite her rural sensibility, Willis began to immerse herself in urban designs. She found that her interests ran parallel to those of San Francisco architects like William Wurster and Joseph Esherick.
Willis' first major architectural project was the conversion of three Victorian buildings into a retail complex on Union Street in San Francisco. Her design, which proved a financial success almost immediately, influenced the renovation of the rest of the street between present-day Gough and Pierce streets.
Meeting the experience and education requirements of the California State Architectural Licensing Board in 1966, Willis became a licensed architect and the only woman in San Francisco with her own firm, Beverly Willis and Associates. This firm assumed a partnership with would-be principal architect David Coldoff that year, a partnership that lasted until 1980. Despite the heavy demands of her practice, Willis also found time to serve on the U.S. Government delegation to the United Nations conference on Habitat, become a trustee and founder of the National Building Museum in 1976, and serve as the President of the California Chapter of the National Institute of Architects in 1979.
Willis' interest in the issues that affect planning, population density, and land-use economics with respect to large-scale development manifested itself in the creation of the computer program CARLA (Computerized Approach to Residential Land Analysis) in the 1970's. The software was developed by Willis with Eric Tiescholz and Jochen Eigen. With CARLA's completion and implementation, Willis and Associates became one of the first architectural firms to incorporate computers into the routine practices of design and land development.
Projects such as the prototype for the regional computer centers of the IRS and master-planning for a new town situated in Aliamanu Valley, Hawaii (1975), are good examples of her unique philosophy of design.
Throughout the 1970s, Willis' firm concentrated on large- scale housing and new-community planning and design. By espousing architecture of rural pragmatism and rooting it in ancient images and myths, Willis offered something new to the intellectual landscape of architectural design.
In 1997, the National Building Museum published Willis' book, Invisible Images: The Silent Language of Architecture, in which she describes her buildings and design philosophy. In 1980, she was elected to the American Institute of Architects College of Fellows. In 1984, Willis received an honorary doctorate in Fine Arts from Mount Holyoke College.
By the early 1980s, Willis' design focus shifted to urban structures like the Yerba Buena Gardens redevelopment project (1980) and the San Francisco Ballet Association Building (1984). Smaller, but no less important, projects include Nob Hill Court (1971), Pacific Point Condominiums (1972), the Greenwich Apartment (1978), the Margaret Hayward Playground Building (1978), the (unbuilt) Shown Winery (1986), and the Mr. and Mrs. Richard Goeglin Pool House and Sculpture (1988).
Willis relocated her office and residence to New York City in 1991. Willis founded in 1994 the Architectural Research Institute, Inc. (through which the Manhattan Village Academy was designed). In 2002, she founded the Beverly Willis Architecture Foundation, and she presently (2008) serves as the foundation's president. Her work and community leadership have been widely published (see bibliography). She is a founding trustee of the National Building Museum (1975-present). The Beverly Willis Library is located at the National Building Museum.
Source
Much of the information in the biography was culled from the biography written for Beverly Willis by Nicolai Ouroussoff and included in Invisible Images: The Silent Language of Architecture, published in 1997 by the National Building Museum, Washington, DC.
Scope and Content
The Beverly Willis Architectural Papers span the years 1954 to 1998 and are comprised primarily of records documenting Willis' work as an architect in San Francisco between 1960 and 1990. The collection documents the application of computers to architectural design and land analysis, the development of CARLA (Computerized Approach to Residential Land Analysis) in the 1970s, the history of twentieth-century urban planning, particularly in San Francisco; and the contribution of women to twentieth-century American architecture. Willis, a noted artist, photographer, teacher, and writer, employed the full range of visual arts and design skills to influence and guide architectural projects of major significance.
The bulk of the collection is comprised of Willis and Associates project files from the period 1960 to 1990. Projects range from private residences and residential developments to institutions, such as the San Francisco Ballet Association Building; and urban development projects, most notably the Yerba Buena Gardens project in downtown San Francisco. Also included are records and design documents for Aliamanu Valley New Town, a military base in Hawaii that was the first major project designed with CARLA, computer software for architectural design created by Willis; and records documenting the development of CARLA.
Project files are comprised of presentation drawings, slope analysis drawings, site plans, maps, cut-and-fill analysis plans, sketches, conceptual design drawings, construction drawings, as well as correspondence, research files, contracts, environmental impact statements and studies, financial records, and feasibility studies. There are records for more than 150 projects. Drawings are large folio, pen-and- ink or watercolor on paper, linen, or mylar. Some are heightened with color.
Also included is a series documenting the development of CARLA, Computerized Approach to Residential Land Analysis, in the 1970s. Beverly Willis was interested in issues that affected planning, population density, and land-use economics in relation to large-scale development. Along with Eric Tiescholz and Jochen Eigen, she developed a program that enabled architects, with the use of computers, to develop site plans and design techniques in a fraction of the time required by the old methodology. Records documenting the development of CARLA include computer tapes, correspondence, flow charts, memos, and Jochen Eigen's notes on interfacing CARLA with a computer mapping program in 1974.
The collection also contains a series of Publications, Brochures, and Clippings, which includes biographical information on Willis, Miscellaneous Project Records, and a video of the Yerba Buena Gardents development.
Some of the information in the scope and content note was taken from an independent appraisal of the collection.
Arrangement
Arrangement
This collection is organized into seven sections. The main section is devoted to Project Files, with project numbers listed in chronological order (with a few exceptions). Project materials are stored in cartons. Oversize materials are stored in folders in drawers. Other sections are: Publications, Brochures and Clippings; CARLA Records; Miscellaneous Project Papers; Presentation Documents; Ephemera; and Beverly Willis Media (two videos produced in 1985). Additional project records are stored separately and identified by carton number in a file-level inventory available at the repository and in the series descriptions in the finding aid.
Other Finding Aid
Other Finding Aid
A file-level inventory of letter- and legal-size project records is available at the repository.
Index Terms
Willis, Beverly, 1928-; Willis and Associates; architect; San Francisco (Calif.); Architectural drawings; Architects and community; Housing - - United States; San Francisco (Calif.) - - Architecture; Urban planning; Architecture - - computer-aided design
Contents List
- Publications, Brochures, and Clippings, 1954-1998 (Box-folder 2:1-3:7)
  This series is comprised primarily of the contents of three large binders containing Willis firm brochures and other publicity materials and newspaper and magazine clippings. It also contains "Eight Projects, 1975-1988," a publication highlighting eight Willis projects with descriptions and slides, and a 1998 curriculum vitae.
  Arranged by format.
  - Articles and Brochures, 1954-1988 (Box-folder 2:1-2:10)
    Publicity materials from Willis' firm, and newspaper and magazine clippings about major Willis projects in San Francisco. Also includes a biographical article about Willis and two copies of Willis' book, Invisible Images: The Silent Language of Architecture. Also included are two postcard prints of Willis paintings from 1956 and 1961 and a copy of an arts supplement to the student newspaper that Willis edited when she was an art student at the University of Hawaii in the 1950s.
    These items were removed from binders and left in the original order, which is roughly reverse chronological. Clippings are inter-filed with publicity materials.
  - Professional Qualifications Brochure, Willis and Associates, 1968 (Box-folder 2:11)
  - "Eight Projects, 1975-1988," 1975-1988, Includes color slides (Box-folder 3:1-3)
  - Article, "Beverly Willis: One Woman's Story," by Cynthia Chapin Davidson, 1991 (Box-folder 3:4, Box 2)
  - Book Proposal, "The Quest for Home," by Beverly Willis and Nicolai Ourousoff, ca. 1996 (Box-folder 3:5)
  - Invisible Images: The Silent Language of Architecture, by Beverly Willis, 1997, 1 volume (Box-folder 3:6, Box 2 (additional copy))
  - Curriculum Vitae, 1998 (Box-folder 3:7, Box 2 (additional copy))
- Project Files, 1958-1998 (Map-case 1:1-15:2, Carton 1-49, Box 2-3)
  Project Files span the period 1958 to 1998 and document projects ranging from private residences and residential developments to institutions, such as the San Francisco Ballet Association Building; and urban development projects, most notably the Yerba Buena Gardens project in downtown San Francisco. Also included are records and design documents for Aliamanu Valley New Town, a military base in Hawaii that was the first major project designed with CARLA, computer software for architectural design created by Willis, and sketches of unbuilt structures designed for writer Alex Haley.
  The series is comprised of presentation drawings, slope analysis drawings, site plans, maps, cut-and-fill analysis plans, sketches, conceptual design drawings, construction drawings, as well as correspondence, research files, contracts, environmental impact statements and studies, financial records, and feasibility studies. There are records for more than 150 projects. Drawings are large folio, pen-and-ink or watercolor on paper, linen, or mylar. Some are heightened with color.
  Drawings and other oversize materials are arranged by project number. Other project records are stored separately and identified by carton number. They are indexed in a file-level inventory available at the repository and in the series descriptions in the finding aid.
  - Project 0101: Warehouse Offices, Honolulu, Hawaii, 1958 (Map-case 1:1)
    Drawing of entry into office suites in a concrete tilt-up building.
  - Project 0131: Bank of Marin, Marin County, California, 1963 (Map-case 1:2)
    - Design Sketch
  - Project 0132: Corning Shopping Center, 1959 (Map-case 1:3)
    - Presentation Drawing
    - Consulting Facade Colors
  - Project 0183: United Vintners Inc. Asti No. 1, Asti, California, 1961 (Map-case 1:3)
    Master plan for grounds around entry, guard enclosure and fencing.
    - Master Site Plan
  - Project 0228: Union Street Stores No. 2, San Francisco, California, 1963 (Map-case 1:4)
    Design for an addition in rear of a commercial retail building in San Francisco.
    - Building Plan, 3 pages
    - Construction Drawings, 13
    - Presentation Drawings, 1
    - Photographs
    - Project Overview
  - Project 0229: Duc Elliot Builders, Foster City, California, 1963 (Map-case 1:5)
    Design of apartment building. Unbuilt.
    - Presentation Drawings
  - Project 0245: Campbell-Ewald No. 2, San Francisco, California, 1964 (Map-case 1:6)
    Design, construction drawings and supervision for renovation of 560 Pacific Street office building in San Francisco. Converted from Barbary Coast whore house lodging.
    - Construction Drawings
    - Film of Building Design
  - Project 0268: Volcano Schoolhouse, Volcano, California, 1964 (Map-case 1:7)
    Design, construction drawings and supervision for renovation and restoration of an 1855 one-room school house into a 3-bedroom residence in Volcano, California.
    Extended Description: A "ghost town" three hours from San Francisco, Volcano, California, was once home to 10,000 miners that worked the original mother-lode of the gold rush. When Willis first saw the deteriorating buildings in the early sixties, the town's one hundred residents survived on weekend tourist trade.
    Built in 1855, a one-room schoolhouse with boarded up bell tower and crumbling foundations was redesigned by Willis as her personal weekend retreat. Gutting the interior, Willis created a two-story living area in one half of the space, and stacked a master bedroom suite over a small kitchen and two bedrooms in the other half. The boys and girls restrooms were converted to half baths, and the original wood flooring was sanded and stained.
    The exterior was fully restored, including bell tower and stone foundations. A deck and swimming pool were added to the outdoor "playground," a modern contrast to the original merry-go-round and chin-up bars.
    - Construction Drawings, 4
    - Site Plan, 4
  - Project 0320: Adlaw Partnership, Oakland, California, 1966 (Map-case 1:8)
    The project included the design and creation of construction drawings and providing supervision for office building facade and lobby renovation.
    - Building Plan, 1
    - Design Sketches, 2
    - Elevations, 1
    - Presentation Drawings, 1
  - Project 0336: Office Building Lobby Renovation, San Francisco, California, 1966 (Map-case 1:9)
    Design, construction drawings and supervision for office building lobby renovation.
    - Presentation Drawings, 1
  - Project 0377: Bayview Community Center A-1, San Francisco, California, 1966 (Map-case 1:10)
    Conceptual design for renovation.
    - Presentation Drawings, 1 set of 18 pages
  - Project 0378: Union Street Beautification, San Francisco, California, 1966 (Map-case 1:11)
    Conceptual design for beautification of Union Street, including parking and street lighting and signage.
    - Conceptual Design Drawings, 11-page proposal
    - Design Sketches, 1
    - Presentation Drawings, 1
  - Project 0383: Herrmann's Cost Plus Headquarters, San Francisco, California, 1967 (Map-case 1:12)
    Interior design.
    - Design Sketches
  - Project 0387: San Mateo County Medical Society No. 2, San Mateo, California, 1967 (Map-case 1:13)
    Design for new building that was not built because funds could not be raised.
    - Building Plan, 1
    - Construction Drawings, 20
    - Design Sketches, 2
    - Elevations, 2
    - Site Plan, 5
  - Project 0421: Jackson Square, San Francisco, California, 1967 (Map-case 1:14)
    Initial site plan analysis of Jackson Square building types within the proposed historical district.
    - Site Plan
  - Project 0424: Cooperage New Site Investigation, 1967 (Map-case 1:15)
    Consulting for Cooperage new site investigation.
    - Construction Drawings, 8
  - Project 0480: Julius Castle Restaurant, San Francisco, California, 1969 (Map-case 1:16)
    Interior Design for Julius Castle Restaurant.
    - Details, 5
    - Construction Drawings, 5
  - Project 0507: Stanford University, Santa Rose, California, 1969 (Map-case 1:17)
    Created customized floor plans and made design modifications suitable for classrooms.
    - Presentation Drawings
    - Elevations
  - Project 0537: Alex Haley Residence, Yosemite, California, 1970 (Map-case 1:18)
    Conceptual design and model. Unbuilt. (land sale corrupt)
    - Building Plan
    - Site Plan
  - Speedspace Sales, 1971 (Carton 8)
    Contracts and Proposals.
  - Project 0563: Austin Estates, 1971 (Map-case 1:19)
    Project required the architect to customize floor plans, make design modifications to standard mobile modular house and site multiple residences for Speedspace.
    - Presentation Drawings
  - Project 0570: Diamond Heights Townhouses, 1971 (Map-case 1:20)
    Design, construction drawings and supervision for Diamond Heights Townhouses. Project filled a full block-area with common open space and children's play yards in the middle of the block.
    - Presentation Drawing
  - Project 0577: Pacific Point, Pacifica, California, 1971 (Map-case 1:21)
    Site study.
    - Presentation Drawing
    - Elevation
  - Project 0594: Vine Terrace Apartments (also Nob Hill Court), San Francisco, California, 1971 (Map-case 1:22)
    Design, construction drawings and supervision for a 48 unit apartment building.
    Extended Description: Sited in downtown San Francisco, a major issue in the design of this 48 unit apartment complex was the need to create a quiet retreat sheltered from the noisy interference and potential dangers of urban life. An image of medieval cities with their protective walls was evoked in Willis' mind. At Nob Hill Court, the medieval wall becomes inhabitable space with a fortress-like facade. The building turns away from the threatening presence of the street to focus on a peaceful open air courtyard interior to the site. A two-story entry lobby with sweeping circular stair is carved from the parking garage that forms the base of the building and the private court.
    Willis transforms the issue of security into a sense of permanency by maximizing the plan and volume of the primary living space of each unit. Large windows flood the interior spaces with light; door and ceiling moldings provide rich details that offer a textural contrast with the plaster walls. Fireplaces, a traditional symbol of home, contribute to the ambiance of warmth and serenity.
    The facade of the building, reminiscent of a stone outcropping, is softened by the use of wood shingles. The mullioned patterns of the wood windows further reduce the scale, offering a degree of detail found in single-family homes.
    - Building Plan
    - Construction Drawing, 39
    - Section
    - Site Plan
  - Project 0599: Halsted's Funeral Home, San Francisco, California, 1971 (Map-case 1:23)
    Design, construction drawings and supervision for minor renovation to Halsted's Funeral Home.
    - Design Sketches, 6
    - Site Plan
  - Project 0610: Union City/Regency Apartments, Union City, California, 1973 (Map-case 1:24)
    Master planning for multi-family housing.
    - Construction Drawings, 1 set of 25 pages
  - Project 0613: Paradise Cay, Marin County, California, 1972 (Map-case 2:1, Map-case 7:12, Map-case 1:25)
    Master planning for a multi-family housing development.
    - Presentation Drawings, 6 (Map-case 2:1, 7:12)
    - Conceptual Design Drawings, 8
    - Design Sketches, 24
  - Project 0623: Hayward Townhouses, San Marin, California, 1972 (Map-case 2:2)
    Design, construction drawings and supervision for multi-family residences.
    - Cut and Fill Analysis
    - Master Site Plan, 1
    - Slope Analysis, Computer Drawn, 1
    - Site Areas of Common Slope, 1
    - Site Topography, 1
  - Project 0628: Pacific Point Condominiums, 1972 (Carton 1)
    Specifications and Details.
  - Project 0635: Crestview Falcon, 1973 (Map-case 2:3)
    - Site Plans, 3
  - Project 0643: Hayward No. 2, 1973 (Carton 5)
    - Detailed Site Design
  - Project 0654: 12 Oaks Village, 1974 (Map-case 2:4)
    Master planning and conceptual design for condominiums; unbuilt.
    - Conceptual Design Drawings, 7
    - Presentation Drawings, 2
  - Project 0657: Mesa Hill No. 2, El Paso, Texas, 1974 (Map-case 2:5)
    Master planning for multi-family housing; unbuilt. CARLA project.
    - Topography and Depth of Cut and Fill (Computer plotted)
  - Project 0660: Aliamanu Valley New Town, Honolulu, Hawaii, 1975 (Map-case 2:6, Carton 5, Box-folder 3:8-9, Map-case 1:26)
    - Illustration of Zones
    - Depth of Expansive Soil, 1
    - Presentation Drawings, 11
    - Reports, 2 copies
    - Site Drainage Analysis, 1
    - Site Perspective, Computer plotted, 1
    - Slope Class Analysis, Computer generated, 3 pages
    - Site feasibility planning
    - Site conceptual design
    - Blank feasibility checklist